# Petr Stepanov

Material Scientist. Nuclear Chemist.



stepanovps@gmail.com



419-496-86-02



petrstepanov.com



scholar.petrstepanov.com

# Objective

Highly motivated Ph.D. student with expertise in gamma spectroscopy, positron annihilation spectroscopy, microscopy, and nuclear physics. A strong background in computational techniques, web applications, and desktop software development. More than five years in UI and UX design.

Graduating in April 2019. Seeking to either apply for a position in a National Laboratory. Wishing to become an effective member of a research group as a post-doctorate fellow or find a steady position in the industry.

Authorized to work in the US on Optional Practical Training (OPT) in the following areas: physics, chemistry, and computer science. Will consider visa sponsorship (H1B) offers.

## **Education**

#### **Bowling Green State University**

Aug 2014 → now

@Bowling Green, OH, USA

Doctor of Philosophy in photochemical sciences.

Dissertation topic: Development of positron annihilation spectroscopy: from experimental setups to advanced processing software.

#### **British Higher School of Art and Design**

Dec 2011 → Feb 2012

@Moscow, Russia

Intensive: graphical design and visual communications.

#### **National Research Nuclear University**

Sep 2004 → Feb 2011

@Moscow, Russia

Bachelor and Master of Science in solid-state physics.

Thesis topic: Radiation defect studies of nuclear power plant vessel steels utilizing positron lifetime annihilation spectroscopy.

# Work experience

#### Freelance UI/UX Designer and Frontend Developer

Aug 2014  $\rightarrow$  now

Working on branding identity guidelines for a number of startups. Designing interactive prototypes and writing agile user stories. Slicing mockups into interactive HTML and responsive CSS. Creating micro-interactions: CSS animations and transitions.

Contributing to the frontend part. Working on gulp build scripts, writing SCSS from scratch. Mostly worked with applications with Node.js, EJS, Mongo.DB and modular JavaScript.

As a part of a team worked on cross-platform mobile applications with lonic framework.

#### Research Assistant, Software Developer

Aug 2014 → now

@Bowling Green State University, OH, USA

Material science research, interaction of ionizing radiation with matter, radiation defects in solids, radiation chemistry. Gammaspectroscopy. Positron annihilation spectroscopy. Maintaining and tune-up of fast-timing ORTEC and Canberra electronics. Manufacturing of the radioactive positron sources.

Developing desktop software solutions (C++, ROOT) for acquisition, storing and treatment of raw experimental data and development and verification of theoretical models. Developing websites for research groups and international meetings and conferences.

Apr 2011 → Aug 2014

@Gridnine Systems, Moscow, Russia

Prototyping conceptual wireframes and visual mockups for web applications (Photoshop, Illustrator).

Developing frontend part of a number of corporate web applications (Google Web Toolkit, JavaScript, Backbone.js and Require.js). Responsive layout with SASS and LESS. Doing some server-side backend programming (Java).

Computer Science Teacher Oct 2009 → May 2011

@Phys-Tech College at Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology (MIPT), Moscow, Russia

Provided instruction and guidance to high school students on following computer courses: advanced C++ programming, markup on the web, Photoshop and 3D Studio Max.

Research Scientist Sep 2008 → Apr 2011

@Institute for Theoretical and Experimental Physics (ITEP), Moscow, Russia

Application of positron lifetime spectroscopy for studying the radioactive-induced defects in steels. Monte-Carlo particle simulations with Fortran 95. Maintaining software for CAMECA tomographic atom probe (MSVC). Application of CERN ROOT libraries for fitting and analysis of experimental spectra.

# Recent publications

- Stepanov, P. S.; Selim, F. A.; Stepanov, S. V.; Bokov, A. V.; Ilyukhina, O. V.; Duplâtre, G.; Byakov, V. M. Interaction of positronium with dissolved oxygen in liquids. *Physical Chemistry Chemical Physics* **2020**.DOI: 10.1039/C9CP06105C
- Stepanov, P. S.; Selim, F. A.; Stepanov, S. V.; Byakov, V. M. A Model for Joint Processing of LT and CDB Spectra of Dielectric Nano-sized Powders. AIP Conference Proceedings 2019, 2182 (1), 040004. DOI: 10.1063/1.5135836
- Stepanov, P. S.; Selim, F. A.; Stepanov, S. V.; Byakov, V. M. Positron and positronium in Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub> nanopowders. AIP Conference Proceedings 2019, 2182 (1), 050008. DOI: 10.1063/1.5135851
- Zhang, L.; Wu, J.; Stepanov, P.; Haseman, M.; Zhou, T.; Winarski, D.; Saadatkia, P.; Agarwal, S.; Selim, F. A.; Yang, H.; et al. Defects and solarization in YAG transparent ceramics. *Photonics Research* 2019, 7 (5), 549 DOI: 10.1364/prj.7.000549
- Saadatkia, P.; Stepanov, P.; Selim, F. A. Photoconductivity of bulk SrTiO3 single crystals at room temperature. Materials Research Express 2018, 5 (1), 016202 DOI: 10.1088/2053-1591/aaa094
- Stepanov, S.; Byakov, V.; Duplâtre, G.; Stepanov, P.; Bokov, A. Track Effects in Positronium Formation. Acta Physica Polonica A 2017, 132 (5), 1461–1466 DOI: 10.12693/aphyspola.132.1461
- Stepanov, P.; Stepanov, S.; Byakov, V.; Selim, F. Developing New Routine for Processing Two-Dimensional Coincidence Doppler Energy Spectra and Evaluation of Electron Subsystem Properties in Metals. *Acta Physica Polonica A* 2017, 132 (5), 1628–1633 DOI: 10.12693/aphyspola.132.1628.
- Ji, J.; Colosimo, A. M.; Anwand, W.; Boatner, L. A.; Wagner, A.; Stepanov, P. S.; Trinh, T. T.; Liedke, M. O.; Krause-Rehberg, R.; Cowan, T. E.; et al. ZnO Luminescence and scintillation studied via photoexcitation, X-ray excitation and gamma-induced positron spectroscopy. Scientific Reports 2016, 6 (1), 31238 DOI: 10.1038/srep31238
- Stepanov, S. V.; Byakov, V. M.; Zvezhinskiy, D. S.; Duplâtre, G.; Dubov, L. Y.; Stepanov, P. S.; Perfiliev, Y. D.; Kulikov, L. A. Premelting as studied by positron annihilation and emission Mössbauer spectroscopies. *Journal of Physics: Conference Series* 2016, 674, 012018 DOI: 10.1088/1742-6596/674/1/012018
- Colosimo, A. M.; Ji, J.; Stepanov, P. S.; Boatner, L. A.; Selim, F. A. Scintillation of Un-doped ZnO Single Crystals. *MRS Advances* **2016**, *1* (2), 121–126 DOI: 10.1557/adv.2015.60
- Stepanov, S. V.; Byakov, V. M.; Duplâtre, G.; Zvezhinskiy, D. S.; Stepanov, P. S.; Zaluzhnyi, A. G. Early processes in positron and positronium chemistry: possible scavenging of epithermal e by nitrate ion in aqueous solutions. *Journal of Physics: Conference Series* 2015, 618, 012003 DOI: 10.1088/1742-6596/618/1/012003
- Stepanov, P. S.; Byakov, V. M.; Zaluzhnyi, A. G. The use of positron spectroscopy for revealing the nanosized structures in liquid mixtures. Identification of n-propanol nanoagglomerates in aqueous solutions. *Russian Journal of Physical Chemistry A* 2014, 88 (4), 685–690 DOI: 10.1134/s003602441404027x

### **Material Research Skills**

#### **Characterization facilities**

Positron Lifetime and Doppler Broadening Annihilation Spectroscopy (PALS, DBAR). Atom Probe Tomography (ATP). Scanning Electron Microscopy (SEM). Transmission electron microscopy (TEM). Atomic Force Microscopy (AFM). UV-VIS Spectroscopy. Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy (FTIR).

#### **Material processing**

High-temperature annealing. Wet chemical etching. Electrical Contact Fabrication. Sample polishing.

# **Computer Skills**

#### Software

Scientific packages: Wolfram Mathematica, Maple.

Markup: LaTeX, MS Office Suite, Zotero.

Data plotting: OriginLab, Gnuplot, QtiPlot, SciDaVis, Grapher, Adobe Products.

#### **Desktop development**

Java and Swing, C/C++ and Qt, GNU Automake, CERN ROOT Framework, PHP, Fortran.

#### UI/UX design

Figma, Sketch, InVision Studio, Adobe XD, Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Illustrator, Inkscape, Blender.

#### **Frontend**

HTML, CSS (LESS and SASS), Bootstrap, responsive web design, JavaScript and jQuery, npm, gulp, CommonJS, AngularJS, React.js and Backbone.js. Google Web Toolkit. WordPress themes development.

# Scientific projects

During my Ph.D. career I've developed a number of desktop software for data analysis and spectra interpretation. The scientific library of my choice is <a href="CERN ROOT framework">CERN ROOT framework</a>. It offers numerous packages for histogram manipulation, fitting and plotting as well as data storage and graphical user interface classes.

#### **TLIST Processor**

Software is designed to process two-dimensional energy spectra and output one-dimensional coincidence broadened Doppler spectrum. A background fitting and subtraction technique is developed and implemented. View on GitHub.

#### **SW Calculator**

The program calculates S and W parameters of the 511 keV peak of the annihilation radiation. The software estimates the values of the binding electron energies by fitting the CDB spectrum with contributions from e+ annihilation on electrons with different wave functions. View on GitHub.

#### **RooPositron**

A flexible terminal-based positron lifetime fitting software. GUI is in progress. The software supports deconvolution of lifetime spectra into the conventional multiexponential model as well as trapping model. Integration of custom fitting models. <u>View on GitHub</u>.

### **Conferences**

Oral talk "Positions and Ps in Al2O3 Nanopowders".

#### International Workshop on Physics with Positrons (JPos17)

Sept 2017

@Jefferson Lab, Newport News, VA, USA

Poster "A routine of background subtraction from two-dimensional Doppler broadened spectra".

#### 12th International Workshop on Positron and Positronium Chemistry (PPC12)

Sept 2017

@Maria Curie-Sklodowska University, Lublin, Poland

Poster "Developing new routine for processing two-dimensional coincidence Doppler energy spectra".

#### **Ohio Photochemical Society Meeting (Oops)**

May 2017

@Maumee Bay Lodge & Conference Center, Maumee, OH, USA

Poster "Developing new routine for background subtraction in two-dimensional coincidence Doppler broadening spectroscopy".

#### 58th Electronic Materials Conference (EMC)

Jun 2016

@University of Delaware, Newark, DE, USA

Oral talk "High-Sensitivity Measurements of Defects in ZnO by Means of Digital Coincidence Doppler Broadening of Positron Annihilation Spectroscopy".

#### Annual Spring Meeting of the APS Ohio-Region

Apr 2016

@University of Delaware, Newark, DE, USA

Oral talk "Identification of chemical environment of defects in ZnO by means of digital coincidence Doppler broadening of positron annihilation radiation".

Ohio Inorganic Weekend Nov 2015

@Bowling Green State University, OH, USA

Poster "Approaching Structural Defect Characterization and their Chemical Identification by Means of Coincidence Doppler Broadening of Annihilation Radiation"

#### 41st Polish Seminar on Positron Annihilation (PSPA-13)

Sep 2013

@Maria Curie-Sklodowska University, Lublin, Poland

Oral talk "Application of positron spectroscopy for detection of nanostructures in alcohol-aqueous mixtures".

### Scientific associations

American Physical Society (since 2016)

The Ohio Academy of Science (since 2016)

### Professional networks

- Check out my portfolio on Dribbble.
- Look up some of my code on GitHub.
- Find my professional contacts on Linkedin.
- Get familiar with my <u>scientific career on ResearchGate</u>.
- Skim through a list of my publications on Google Scholar.

### **Interests**

Snowboarding, rollerblading, hiking, working on cars and bikes, footbag.